== ×ÖÄ»ÖÆ×÷£º²¨Ê¿¶Ù ==
== 字幕制作：波士D ==
In the 49th year of Kang Xi's reign
大清康熙四十九年
It was the 11th month
庚寅十壹月
Emperor Kang Xi escorted the Queen Mother
康熙帝玄烨奉皇太後
To stay in the Summer Resort in Changde
v跸承德府行m避署山f
Accompanying them were Prince Yunnai
S{的有太子允i
Prince Yong,4th son of the Emperor
皇四子和T雍H王胤G
And many imperial concubines and princes
和後妃 、 子 、 勒及王公大臣等
The Summer Resort has an area of 16 square miles
避署山f周十六Y
With a lake on its left and mountains on its right
左湖右山
The mountains stretch from north to west
山萦杀倍西
With green valleys and pine forests
有梨渖焦 、 松林山谷回抱如h
And verdant paths with scenic views
酱淝玑埃朝夕
A waterfall comes from a valley of the west
瀑源碜晕魃焦
It starts from the tip of an emerald rock
垂于ゴ溲抑巅
And is streaming down to the lake
玉珠w，晴雷夏雪，∮诤中
Seemingly harnessed over the lake is a rainbow bridge
湖岸曲榭辇w，L蚝珩{
It is a scenic delight
L景怡人
On the 11th day of the 11 month, the Emperor
十壹月十壹日，皇上率太子允i
went to hunt with Prince Yunnai and Prince Yong
和T雍H王胤G等
During a hunting chase in Mulan
在木m狩C
Don't kill it
e⑺浪
Seems like it can't survive
看幼踊畈涣肆
Don't waste the good stuff
e糟蹋材料
Drink its blood while it's still alive
趁活的r候喝碗鹿血吧
Deer blood£¿
鹿血？
It's good stuff,gives you energy
好|西啊，鹿血滋a
Makes you strong and live long
鹿茸延年益
Good
好
Kill it
⑺浪
Drink it while it's still hot
趁岷
The fresher the better
越新r越a
What to do after having this good stuff£¿
a完了怎打l？
After having this,you¡­
a完了，就…
Nonsense
胡f八道
It's a bit smelly
不e，就是有c腥
Deer blood smells,human flesh has a sour taste
然了，鹿血腥，人肉酸
Human flesh is sour£¿
人肉酸？
What£¿ You ate human flesh before£¿
怎麽了？吃^人肉？
Why not£¿
怎麽]吃^？
Everyone who went to war with the Emperor
跟皇上在准噶打^仗的人
has tasted human flesh and horse piss
l]吃^人肉喝^R尿
But not all human flesh is sour
有壹N人肉不酸
Here's a sweet one coming
不酸的砹
Who give you permission to hunt here£¿
什麽人叫到@捍颢C？
Tell me,who give you permission to hunt here£¿
f，什麽人叫到@泶颢C？
What£¿
怎麽？
You raise these deer£¿
鹿是B的幔
Of course not
然不是我B的
But I'm in charge of all the deer in Mulan
可是木m的鹿是我管的
Tell me,who give you permission to hunt here£¿
告V我，什麽人叫到@捍颢C
My old man
我老子
Your old man£¿
老子？
Why your old man can give you permission
老子有什麽嗔
to hunt in this place£¿
叫到@捍颢C？
Don't you know the Emperor forbids
不知道皇上旨意
hunting within 200 miles of Mulan£¿
木m周砂傺Y不准打C幔
Sure,no one is allowed to hunt here
我然知道，e人打不得
Except me
我老子可以打
That doesn't make sense
~Z理
Why the hell would you be allowed to hunt here£¿
什麽老子可以打C？
It is because¡­
因旨意…
the order is given by my old man
就是我老子下的
Come and meet Prince Yong
不^雍H王
Your Highness,here's your humble maid Lijia
奴才李佳氏叩王
My lord,she's rude and has offended you
王，她太oY了，敢冒犯王
Get up¡­
起怼
Lijia,you're a member of the Han clan, right£¿
李佳氏，是h人投旗的了？
Yes
是
Where do you live£¿
住在哪Y？
The cottage next to the stable
就在前面R旁有水的小屋子Y
So you're in charge of the imperial stable£¿
是管RR圈的？
Yes
是的
Your Highness
叩王
Get up¡­
起怼
In the 8th month the following year
第二年八月
News of stable maid Lijia's pregnancy
避署山f鞅榱
Has spread through the Summer Resort
m女李佳氏言械南息
The Resort was guarded as heavily as the Palace
行m森辣戎大
Then who's the baby's father£¿
N玉何人呢？
Emperor Kang Xi was indignant
H令康熙大怒
It must be him
除了他有l
Summon Prince Yong
把雍H王
Yes
喳
According to Vol.247 of Kang Xi's Chronicles
根}祖仁皇帝247卷的d
In the 50th year of Kang Xi's reign
康熙五十年
which happened to be the 6th month of 1 71 1A.D
也就是公元壹七壹壹年六月丙辰
Prince Yong went to Rehe to visit his father
皇四子和T雍H王胤G赴岷诱安
The visit was only an excuse
其安是掩的~句
In fact Kang Xi had known about Lijia's pregnancy
H上是皇上得知李佳氏身蚜甲
And was indignant
大怒
He reprimanded Prince Yong
τ河H王痛加斥
And Lijia was not allowed to give birth in the palace
同r不准李佳氏在m扰R盆
On the 13th day of the 8th month
在八月十三日
A kind old palace maid
由壹嵝牡睦m女
Secretly helped Lijia to give birth
偷偷地李佳氏接生
Prince Yong's 4th son was born at midnight
在子r生了雍H王的第四皇子弘
Among the 208 emperors in Chinese history
也就是中汛二百零八皇帝中
He was the only one who lived to be 89
唯壹活到八十九q
He had ruled for sixty years
在位六十年
And gave his throne to his heir after he retired
K做了四年太上王
He was Emperor Chien Lung
享圩罡 、 在位最久的乾隆皇帝
In the 59th year of Kang Xi's reign
康熙五十九年庚子九月
The Emperor was 65
玄烨已六十五q
And was still looking for an heir to his throne
因太子允iU而又立 、 立而又U
So worried was he that his hair turned grey
谛诹σ灾马l皆白
An unexpected incident happened
但是A想不到的是
during this hunting trip
在@次狩中
During a group hunt
E然g在中
a ferocious black bear appeared
出F了壹只凶猛o比的黑熊
Your Majesty
皇上
Your grandson Hongli kowtows to you
O汉堰狄
May my grandfather live many thousands of years
fqfqffq
Hongli£¿ Who's Hongli£¿
弘眩磕弘眩
Your Majesty,he's the 4th son of Prince Yong
回皇上，是和T雍H王的第四子
The one who was born in Mulan
在木m出世的弘
Good
好
Hongli
弘
I'm here
O涸
You're raised outside the lmperial Palace
男∩L在外面
and have good martial and equestrian skills
武功Tg都不e
Have you started learning yet£¿
有]有念^啊？
I started learning at four
O核q蒙
I could recite some classic at six
六q可以背永凵f
Do you know how to make couplets£¿
不ψ樱
A little bit
知道壹二
Good,I'll make the first part and you the next
好，我出副上，看
Yes
是
What's the matter£¿
怎麽了？
You know how to make couplets£¿ Want to try£¿
ψ幔恳不要壹？
It's easy. You do it first
那不容易，f吧
I say ¡°up¡±
我f上
I say ¡°down¡±
我ο
I say ¡°big¡±
我f大
I say ¡°small¡±
我π
I say ¡°man¡±
我f人
I say ¡°dog¡±
我狗
I am ¡°big man up¡± here
我是上大人
I am ¡°small dog down¡± below
我是下小狗
Hey you,you¡­
真是，真是的…
Listen
著
Yes
是
A four-sided pavilion has four sides
四方亭，亭四方
Look out the four sides from the four-sided pavilion
四方亭上望四方
All four sides are covering the four directions
四方四方是四方
Long life to my grandpa who lived long
fq，fq
Wishing longevity to the one who lived long
fq前呼fq
Long live long live to the one
fqfqffq
Your humble maid Lijia
奴才李佳氏
Kowtows to Your Majesty
叩fqfqffq
Arise
平身
Thank you,Your Majesty
xfq
It's too shabby here
太陋了
A small hill is famous for the fairies living there
山不在高，有仙t名
A small pond is known for the dragons it has
水不在深，有t`
A shabby room is decorated with my virtues
斯是陋室，惟吾德馨
There's green grass and moss outside
苔痕A上G，草色入青
inside there are scholars but not laymen
笑有儒，往o白丁
This is far from shabby
何陋之有？
It sounds ambitious at our age
小小年o，好大的口
Grandpa,everyone in this room is either
，您看看@g房子
Of imperial descent or high officials
不是子O，就是朝壹品
There's no commoners here
有什麽人是白丁？
You can play the qin and read Buddhist scriptures
可以{素琴，金
Life in this room is quiet and relaxed
oz竹之y耳，o案牍之谛
Good,this analogy is precise and exact
好，用典用得不偏不倚，恰到好
Come here
戆
Yes
喳
Tell me
笠
What are the eight major families of Qing£¿
咱八旗的八大氏族o我
Yes
喳
The Gua'erjia family
瓜佳氏
The Shumulu family
舒穆氏
The Bangla family
邦喇氏
The Dong'e family
鄂氏
The Majia family
R佳氏
The Yi'ergenjue family
伊根X_氏
The Huifa family
xl氏
And the Niugulu family
和o祜氏
Is that all£¿
R了？
Yes
喳
I grant the family name Niugulu to Lijia
n李佳氏o祜氏
When I go back to Beijing with the Queen Mother
朕奉皇太後回銮的r候
Hongli and Niugulu should accompany me
弘押外o祜氏S{同行
And move into Prince Yong's mansion
搬到雍H王府
Yes,Your Majesty
遵旨
Thank you,Your Majesty
xfq
In 61 st year of Kang Xi's reign, on 13th November
康熙六十壹年十壹月十三日
Kang Xi passed away in the evening
甲午戍刻
¡­in Changchun Garden
}祖崩于炒@
In the same year,on 20th day of 1 1th month
同年十壹月二十日辛h
Prince Yong became heir to the throne
雍H王接位，是世宗
After having reigned for thirteen years
改元雍正，在位十三年
he made Hongli his heir
魑挥诤眩改元乾隆
Hongli's title was Chien Lung
乾隆在位六十年
He remained as an emperor for sixty years
又做了三年零四月的太上皇
It was a golden era of the Qing dynasty
享郯耸九q，是清朝最盛的r期
He had won ten wars
曾打^十次僬
And thus called himself ¡°Old Man of Perfect Ten¡±
所以自封十全老人
Now in the Palace Museum in Taipei
@是F在存在台北故m博物院的
this is Chien Lung's Diadem
乾隆^盔
Mala beads and the queen's phoenix headdress
朝珠和皇後的P冠
And these are Chien Lung's snuff bottles
另外是他用^的鼻
and his treasure box
和他的百箱
It is said that Chien Lung had collected tens and
如@拥那隆珍玩
thousands of treasure pieces like these
f有兹f件之多
Chien Lung liked antiques and paintings
乾隆喜好文玩 、 字
He had composed volumes of poems and lyrics
留下的~有兹f首之多
Some of them might be written by his ministers
然其中有些是臣下代P的
He was really an emperor of arts
但也算是壹L雅的皇帝
These are part of his seals and stationery
@是他的印章和文房四的壹部分
Chien Lung's greatest contribution to literature was£º
清高宗τ谖W上最大I
To form an editorial team of scholars
是O立了四烊^
To edit the Classics in Four Categories
纂了史子集分的四烊
This is a major collection since Ming dynasty
是中自明朝永反蟮渲後的巨著
The editorial team had
四祓^鹊慕M
16 Editors
O正裁官十六人
10Associate editors
副裁官十人
15 Sub-editors
官十五人
3 Chiefeditors
纂官三人
2 Proof readers
校官二人
And 179 scribes and othersupporting staff
有其他分校官179人等
It has atotal of 368 staff
合共368人
And had edited 3470titles
它所著的凡3470部
Which has a total of 79018 volumes
共79018卷
The collection had seven copies
壹共了七份
There were stored in Wen Yuen Court ofthe Palace
分e存在韧⒌奈Yw
In Wen Yuen Court of Yue Ming Garden
A明@的文源w
In Wen Suan Court of Shenyang
沈的文溯w
In Wen Jing Court of Rehe
岷拥奈慕蜷w
In Wen Wei Court of Yangzhou
P州大^堂的文￠w
In Wen Zhong Court ofZhengjiang
江金山寺的文宗w
In Wen Lan Court of Hangzhou
杭州}因寺的文w
Chief EditorJi Xiaolan¡­
冀人o葬耙钥纂官的地位
led the team to complete the editorial work
督促全^同仁把四烊修成功
ofthis classic collection and an index
又依照乾隆的旨意
¡­to the entire collection
出壹部四烊目提要
Ji was a great scholar of the Chien Lung era
o葬笆乔隆年g的大儒
His works included ¡°Notes from Yuewei Hall¡± etc
著作有微草堂P
He was humorous and eloquent
人L趣诙C 、 巧言善q
The eunuchs always wanted a story from him
太O常要他f笑解
Master Ji
o纂
Hmm
好
This is the new editorfrom the lmperial Academy
@是翰林院新派淼木修
Master Chang Fengwu
常大人常P梧
Master Ji
o纂
Fengwu,good,it's a good name
P梧，好，好名字
The day before I was born,my mother had dreamt of
年家母生我的前壹天
A phoenix on a parasol tree
粢了P凰落在梧桐渖
So I was named Feng£¨phoenix£©Wu£¨parasol tree£©
所以叫我P梧
Fengwu,a phoenix on a parasol tree
P梧，P凰落在梧桐渖
So you were called Fengwu, it's a good name
所以叫P梧，好，好名字
Fengwu¡­oh dear
P梧…哎呀
That's too close
好U啊
To what£¿
怎麽了？
Your mother dreamt of a phoenix on a parasol tree
幸好令堂是粢P凰落在梧桐渖
So you're called Fengwu,you're lucky
所以叫P梧
Had she dreamt of a chicken on a banana tree
要是令堂粢u落在芭蕉渖
¡­that's not very good
那就不太好了
What does that mean£¿
怎麽意思？
A phoenix on a parasol tree
怎麽意思？P凰落在梧桐渖
That's why your name is Fengwu,right£¿
不是叫P梧幔
If a chicken lands on a banana tree
要是u落芭蕉
Then it must be Ji¡­
那不就成了u…
Old master¡­
老夫子…
Wait
等壹等
Don't leave now
e走啊
Old master¡­
老夫子
What's the matter¡­
什麽事…
Please tell us a joke
f笑啦
I'm busy now,maybe next time
我忙得很，]有工夫，回^再v
Don't just leave
e走啊…
You have to tell us one¡­
也得壹嘛…
Just a short one
短的啊
Okay¡­a short one
好…我f短的
Once upon a time
那鞍
What happened£¿
那霸貅樱
There was a eunuch
有壹太O
Once upon a time there was a eunuch, what next£¿
那坝幸太O，底下怎麽樱
Next£¿
底下？
Right,what next£¿
是，底下怎麽啦？
Nothing
]有啦
It's that short£¿
就@麽短啊？
Short£¿ There's nothing
短？短的都]有了
Nothing£¿
]有了？
Nothing
]有了
It's that short
就@麽短
Ah¡­this old bastard
哦，@老王八蛋
What£¿
怎麽了？
He's right,do you have anything down there£¿
可不是嘛，底下有幔
I don't
是]有
That old bastard,he's making fun of us
老王八蛋，他挖苦咱
Right,I'll make him pay for this some day
可不是嘛，有壹天
When I get the chance
我叫老兔崽子落在我的手Y
I'll make it very difficult for him
吃不了叫兜著走
Right¡­
Α
Your Majesty
皇上吉祥
Arise
平身
Thank you,Your Majesty
xfq
Where's Master Ji,the Chief Editor£¿
怎麽了？o昀o纂？
He¡­
他…
Must be somewhere to get some fresh air
想必是到外隹烊チ
Right,it's too hot here
@禾崃耍@也y怪
You're busy,please sit down
辛苦了，坐下砻Π
Let's go
咱走了
Yes
喳
Long live Your Majesty
fqffq
That laotouzi £¨old guy£© has left£¿
老^子走了？
You¡­
…
Oh my laotouzi
我的老^子
Laotouzi£¿
老^子？
No¡­long live Your Majesty
不…fqfqffq
Laotouzi£¿ What does that mean£¿
老^子？什麽老^子？
Your Majesty
fq
You're not properly dressed, it's already an offence
衣衫不整，有失wy不f
And you call me laotouzi
要叫我老^子
Right,this is really impolite
就是f啊，有失wy不f啊
And you even dare to call His Majesty laotouzi
敢叫fq老^子
Yes,this is too much
是啊，太不像了
Tell me what laotouzi means
f，什麽叫老^子？
Am I really old £¨lao£©£¿
我，什麽地方老？
You have to give me a good explanation now
今天，f得出名堂磉tT了
Otherwise I'll have your head chopped off
否t的老^子就要的^，f
I'll explain¡­
我f…
Hurry up
快f
Hmm¡­
@…
Lao means to live as long as Heaven
c天同 、 fo疆，^之老
To live as long as Heaven
c天同郏fo疆
Then how about ¡°tou¡±£¿
那麽^呢？
Men can't walk without a head
人o^不走，Bo翅不w
Your Majesty is the head of all people
fq乃f民之首
So this is ¡°tou¡±
^之^
How about ¡°zi¡±£¿
那麽子呢？
It means Your Majesty is the son of Heaven and Earth
fq乃父天母地，^之子
Son of Heaven and Earth
好，父天母地
Laotouzi
老^子
Good,Laotouzi
好，老^子
Lao means to live as long as Heaven
c天同 、 fo疆^之老
Tou means you're head of all people
f民之首^之^
Zi means your parents are Heaven and Earth
父天母地^之子
So Your Majesty is loatouzi
所以皇上是老^子
Loutouzi,my loatouzi
老^子，我的老^子
Come here
戆
Yes
喳
It's hot but Master Ji is allowed
天幔o先生以後
To work here without a shirt
可以光膀子在@|西
It's not your business
用不著多管e事
Yes
喳
You four stay here to sever Master Ji from now on
以後四在@菏毯蚣o先生
To keep him cool and comfortable
oo先生打扇
Yes
喳
Ji Xiaolan was not the only scholar
r呢除了o昀o葬
who was renowned for his humour
以文章诙C名之外
There was also Liu Yong,another scholar
另外有④⑹庵
Who was humorous and eloquent
也是以能言善q忠正幽默名于世
Liu had been a high ranking government official
他^左都R史 、 右都R史
¡­and a scholar of the lmperial Academy
h中堂文Aw大W士
Because of his humour and eloquence
因他人诙C滑稽 、 巧言善q
He won Chien Lung's favour
深得乾隆皇帝的喜
They often made fun of each other
君臣之g也常的_著小玩笑
And here's a story about them
所以飨硪级尉臣Y智的故事
Rong An
容安
Yes,Your Majesty
臣在
Does he look like a hunchback£¿
看像不像_？
Yes,exactly
可不是嘛，俗Zf_上山 ： 前o
It might take him all day
他上上八百六十四犹A
to climb all the 864 steps
可真蚯评习胩斓哪
See,he's breathing heavily
人走r猓R走骠
And really looks like a hunchback
巫吡_
Yes¡­
是…
Come here
戆
Yes
喳
Tell him to hurry up
催他快c
Master Liu,His Majesty wants to talk to you
⒋笕耍皇上f有要事跟商量
Please hurry up
走快刹铰
Okay
好
Hurry up,Master Liu
s快刹桨桑⒋笕
Your¡­
臣…
Oh,my dear Master Liu
哎眩我的⒋笕
It's not easy for you to climb all these steps
上了@麽高的台A，可真蛏虻牧
Your Majesty,Liu Yong kowtow¡­
臣④{，叩…
Long live¡­long live
fqf…ffq
Arise
平身
Thank you,Your Majesty
xfq
Liu Yong
④
Yes,Your Majesty
臣在
Why are you so slow today£¿
怎麽今哼@麽不事？
You're becoming a hunchback
直成了_了
Thank you,Your Majesty
臣x主隆恩
What for£¿
x什麽恩啊？
Thank you for giving me the title ¡°Hunchback¡±
xfq封臣_字
What's that title good for£¿
封_字又有什麽用呢？
From now on,I can have an extra salary of
臣今後
20 thousand a year
每年可以多P扇f摄y子的俸
Why is that so£¿
@是暮握f起？
It was established by the ancestors of Qing
@是大清的祖制
Established by our ancestors£¿
祖制？
Yes,it came from the ancestors
是祖制，祖宗留下淼闹贫
At the time of Emperor Shun Zhi, his titles included£º
治朝，世祖封的是 ：
Titian,Longyun,Dingtong,Jianji
w天 、 隆\ 、 定y 、 建O
Yinrui,Qinwen,Xianwu,Dade
英睿 、 J文 、 @武 、 大德
Honggong,Zhiren,Chunxiao
弘功 、 至仁 、 孝章皇帝
You're an erudite
有W
For each extra title
每多字
An extra sum of 20 thousand was added
就每年加多扇f摄y子的俸
I have blessings from my ancestors
我④祖上有德
And thus get the title ¡°Hunchback¡± from Your Majesty
蒙皇上破例加封_字
I should say thank you to Your Majesty
臣自x主隆恩
I am not giving you the title ¡°Hunchback¡±
朕K非封_
It's nothing serious,it's just a joke
只是@麽壹比方，f著玩的
A monarch always speaks seriously
君o蜓阅
You can't deny what you've said
皇上您f的不能不算啊
If you don't take this seriously
您要是B@字都不算
How can we believe in you£¿
那您以後f的可怎麽算啊
You're the Emperor,you have to keep your word
您是皇上，不能言而o信
Okay,I grant you the extra 20 thousand every year
好吧，每年就多P扇f砂
Thank you,Your Majesty
x主隆恩
Your Majesty¡­
皇上…
Think of something to trick him
壹想法子yy他
So I can revoke his title
然後P他把_字取消
Yes¡­
是…
Okay,arise
好吧，起戆
Thank you,Your Majesty
xfq
The Emperor is leaving now
皇上起{…
Enjoy your extra salary
@扇f摄y子留著慢慢用吧
Yes
是
Oh,that's right
α耍壹c都不e
This extra money is really enough for you
@扇f摄y子蚰用老半天的了
Master Liu,let's wait and see
⒋笕耍您走著瞧吧
Rong An
容安
Yes,Your Majesty
臣在
Master Liu,when His Majesty was climbing the steps
⒋笕耍才皇上上台A的r候
I had wished him good luck
我o皇上念了句喜歌
Wish him to ascend higher with every step
皇上步步高升
Yes
是
Now His Majesty is coming down the steps
如今Z{下台A
You go and wish His Majesty good luck
您也o皇上念删湎哺
And make His Majesty feeling happy
Z{了心Y也高d高d
Doesn't matter,take your time
不要o，慢慢的想
It's not too late if he can do it¡­
只要在朕]有平地登之前
before I set foot on flat ground
就不算晚
Otherwise I'll take back his title
否t朕可要收回_字了
With 20 thousand dollars a year
不然的壹年扇f
After 10 years it'll add up to 200 thousand
十年就二十f
If you are going to live to 80 or even 1 00
要是活百喊耸q的
Then I end up paying pay you a fortune
那我得多花多少X
Yes,that's a huge amount of money
是啊，@Py子可真不少啊
So£¿
怎麽樱
You see¡­
瞧…
Down with every step
步步登矮
Missing every step
步步]著
Slipping with every step
步步落空
Sliding with every step
步步不
Lowering with every step
步步下溜
A step is worse than the next
壹步不如壹步
Your Majesty
fq…
I have made a wish for you¡­
臣想起砹恕
Your Majesty,I wish you
皇上，臣念您
to have smarter descendents
後倒比前高
Each generation is smarter than their elders
您是子Of代，壹比壹高
Good¡­
好…
Thank you,Your Majesty
xfqF臣好
Oh shit,let's go
好他的O子，走
Master Liu,you're really smart
⒋笕耍您真高
And you can keep your extra salary
您啊猴T，是高^去了
Your Majesty,is that title¡­
皇上，就{_字
really worth 20 thousand dollars£¿
真值扇f砂。
He has a reason for this,I can't help
不然怎麽著？他有理嘛
His head is full of vicious ideas
壹肚子乃
You have to think of something
得想主意
He can't have that extra money for free
不能每年白白o他扇f
I'm thinking as we speak
臣正在想著呢
Your Majesty,I have an idea
皇上，臣倒想出主意
What idea£¿
什麽主意？
This¡­
@…
Tell me
f啊
You haven't rewarded him for his good wish yet
他才o您念喜歌，]p他
A reward£¿ That old bastard
p他？@老王八蛋
No,just set up a trap to trick him
不是真的p他，是yy他
How£¿
怎麽y法？
Give him that ring you're wearing
把手上的扳指摘下碣po他
If Liu took it and put it on
④要是手壹接壹戴
then he would have offended the Emperor
您的|西他敢戴，@就是欺君之罪
But you should spare his death punishment
把他死罪免了
And only revoke his title
P他把_字取消不就成了
What if he didn't put the ring on£¿
他要是不戴呢？
Then he is disobeying the Emperor's order
他要是不戴，就打他抗旨不遵
His title should be revoked
_字是得取消
Good idea
好
Liu Yong
④
Wait for the imperial order
臣④候旨
You've just said something very nice
才的吉祥f得不e
I give you this ring as a reward
p扳指戴
Thank you,Your Majesty
xfq
Master Liu,you may put it on
⒋笕耍戴上吧
Liu Yong
④
Yes,Your Majesty
臣在
Why don't you put it on£¿
怎麽不戴上啊？
I dare not to
臣不敢戴
Why£¿ You must think it's cheap,right£¿
不敢？是不是看不上眼，不要啊？
This is a reward from Your Majesty
fqpo臣的|西
I dare not to think it's cheap
臣的焉敢不要
Then why don't you just put it on£¿
要？什麽不戴上它？
If I do,I'm offending the Emperor
戴上，臣有欺君之罪
If I don't,I'm disobeying the Emperor
不戴，臣有抗旨不遵
But you can't keep holding it just like that
那老@麽拖著也不行啊？
I'll give it to my servants and ask them¡­
臣交o手下人
to take it back to my home in Shandong
捎回山|省青州府T城h老家
And place it in our ancestral shrine
供在我祖宗的祠堂Y
But now I'll put it over my hat
F在臣的我先o您著
He wins that ring
又他壹扳指
You must think of something to trick him
壹定要再想法子Ω端
Yes
是
Forty skating beauties from Korea are here
朝rM滑冰美女四十人
They're ready to perform for Your Majesty
候旨在R前I技
Okay,start the performance
好，_始吧
Your Majesty,I have an idea
fq，臣又想起壹k法砹
What idea£¿
什麽k法？
There's an ice hole under that bridge
那虻紫虏皇怯冰窟窿嘛
When the performance is over
等壹表演完了
You ask Liu to jump into that ice hole
就叫④跳冰窟窿
Jump into that ice hole£¿
跳冰窟窿？
You may ask him
等壹，您先他
If a father asks his son to die but the son refuses
父要子亡，子要不亡
What is this£¿
^之什麽？
This is impious
^之不孝
If a monarch asks his subject to die but he refuses
Π。那君要臣死，臣要不死
What is this£¿
^之什麽？
This is disloyalty
^之不忠
Exactly. Your Majesty,if he refused
Π。fq，他要是不跳
Then he's disobeying you
就打他抗旨不遵
You can revoke his title
把_字免掉
What if he did jump£¿
他要跳呢？
Then you call for rescue
R上叫人把他o救起
He's still disloyal because he hasn't died
他]死了也算不忠
You can revoke his title
是把_字免掉
And take back that ring
另外，那扳指也要回
Rong An
容安
Yes,Your Majesty
臣在
Yes
喳
Pass the Emperor's order
骰噬系闹家
Reward each performer with
CnI技的
4 large rolls of silk
每人大卷八z四匹
4 small rolls of silk
大卷五z四匹
Five pairs of silk pouches
大荷包壹Γ小荷包四
Reward each ambassador with
另外晌皇拐
3 rolls of fine silk and 3 rolls of wool
加n文淳\三匹，漳q三匹
And have a banquet in Ziguang Hall
在紫光殿n宴
Thank you,Your Majesty
fqfqffq
Liu Yong
④
Yes,Your Majesty
臣在
There's an old saying
有壹句古Z
I remember only the first part but not the second part
我得上句，不得下句
Please tell me what I've forgotten
想跟教教
I don't deserve to do this
微臣不敢
A father asks his son to die but the son refuses
@…父叫子亡，子要不亡
What is this£¿
^之什麽呢？
This is impious
^之不孝
A monarch asks his subject to die but he refuses£¿
君要臣死，臣要不死呢？
This is disloyal
那就^之不忠
So
既然@麽f
I'm the monarch and you're the subject
我是君，是臣
Now I am asking you to die
我F在叫死
And you go to die now
就死吧
This¡­
@…
Master Liu,accept the imperial order
⒋笕耍您就接旨吧
Now I¡­
臣@…
I'm waiting for the imperial order
臣候旨
What order£¿
候什麽旨？
I told you to die and you just go and die
我叫死，去死就得了嘛
Your Majesty only told me to die
fq只是叫臣去死
But haven't told me how to die
您]有吩咐叫臣怎麽尤ニ
There's an ice hole over there
前面有冰窟窿
You can just jump into that hole
就跳到冰窟窿Y得了
I accept the order
臣遵旨
Is he really jumping£¿
他真跳啊？
What happened£¿
怎麽回事？
Yes¡­
是…
Right,I'll go and ask
Π。我去
Thank you for reminding me,see you later
xx的指c，回，咱回^
Liu Yong has completed your order
臣④交旨
Completed£¿ What£¿
交旨？交什麽旨？
If you're dead then you've completed my order
我死，死了才算交旨
You haven't jumped into the ice hole yet
]往冰窟窿Y跳就回砹
And you think you've completed my order£¿
@算交什麽旨？
Your Majesty,before I jump
fq，臣我要跳
a man in the water stops me
水Y面有壹人把我or住了
Oh£¿
哦？
And he speaks to me
跟我f了拙湓
He tells me to come back and ask Your Majesty
他我回砀皇上示示
¡­before I jump into that ice hole
示完了呢再跳
There's even a man in the water,who's he£¿
水Y居然有人，是l啊？
He's Qu Yuan of the Chu State
是楚的三闾上大夫屈原
Is he the one who was forced to jump into
是f被o道昏君
Miluo River by a tyrant and killed himself£¿
逼他跳I_江自⒌哪屈原呐
Yes,that's Qu Yuan who was forced to jump
正是，被昏君信身奸臣的言
into the Miluo River because a tyrant listened
逼得走投o路
to slanderous talks
跳I_江死了的那屈原
What does he tell you£¿
他跟f什麽碇？
He tells me thus£º
他跟微臣f了@麽删湓，他f
I had met a tyrant so I had to die
我遇昏君死
You've met a smart emperor so you should live
逢明主理活
Go back and ask the Emperor
回去示示
¡­before you come back and die
完了再死也淼眉
And I think
臣想了想
I'm nothing,but Your Majesty's name is important
生死事小，名事大
Though Qu Yuan was killed by a tyrant
屈原m然是被昏君o逼死了
Yet people keep remembering him
可是f民景仰他的心]有死
Every year during Dragon Boat Festival
壹直到F在每年端午
We still have dragon boat races and rice dumplings
大家都船吃粽子o念屈原
We remember Qu Yuan when we have rice dumplings
壹吃粽子就想起屈原
When we remember Qu Yuan
壹想起屈原
We also remember that tyrant
就想起那o道的昏君砹
So he asks me to come back and make sure
所以他叫臣回碚示明白
You're an intelligent and virtuous monarch
您是英明之主 、 有道的明君啊
How can you force an official to die just because of
哪能了每年多P扇f摄y子俸
paying an extra salary of 20 thousand dollars£¿
就逼大臣跳冰窟窿的呢？
My life is nothing but a feather
臣之生死p如毛
Your Majesty's name will last for generations
君之名P乎千古
So I want to make sure
所以臣要示明白
My intelligent and virtuous monarch
我的英明之主，臣的有道明君
Do you want me to die or not£¿
您看臣是死呢？是不死呢？
Well¡­
那…
You don't have to die
就e死了
If I told you to die
我叫死了
Then I would become that tyrant
我不成了z臭f年的昏君了幔
Okay,you don't have to die
好了，甭死了
You stay alive and keep annoying me
活著慢慢的馕野
Yes,Your Majesty
臣遵旨
The 1st month of the 16th year of Chien Lung's reign
乾隆十六年辛未春正月
Chien Lung went to the south with Queen Mother
弘逊罨侍後，首次南巡
He had taken six trips to the south
他和他的祖父康熙壹右擦下江南
Some say he went to visit his real parents
有人髡f他到海甯家
But this is totally groundless
其是完全]有根的
The emperors of Qing dynasty
清朝的皇帝
Went to the Summer Resort in Rehe every year
每年壹定到岷拥谋苁鹕角f
Not only to hide away from the heat in Beijing
名避署
But also keep a leeway for themselves
H上是自己留壹l退路
And to make connections with the Mongolian tribes
也了j蒙古八旗的感情
Trips to the south is also public relations work
下江南也是做做
To maintain good relations with Han people
γ耖g及h人的公共P系
Minor taxes would be waived
所以每到壹都免些苛捐s
And visited those retired ministers and officials
和看看地已告老回l的大臣
Elders were invited to banquets as well
也[[千叟宴，表示敬老尊t
And of course the Emperor might just
然微服出[散散心
Go to the south for his own pleasure
也不能f^]有
Ministers and officials around him
因包在他身的王公大臣
Would never offend him
λ都是唯唯ZZ
By telling the truth
不f壹句真心
If he wanted to know the truth
想真的幔
He had to go to the people
到民g老百姓
So he left the lmperial Palace alone
于是B壹侍l都不
And posed as a merchant
假扮商人
If someone asked questions
有人幔
He would say he's Gao Tianci from Beijing
就f是北京天府的高天n
Honestly,this was a pompous name
f真的天no他的太高了
Boss,is your business good£¿
老板，生意好幔
Just so so¡­
不是了三餐混口…
Sir,how may I be of any help£¿
@位客官什麽事啊？
People in Yangzhou are serious about their tea
fP州人最v究喝茶
Which is the best teahouse here£¿
到底是哪壹家最好啊？
Do you want just tea or tea with food£¿
那要看喝素茶是喝茶
Well,what's the difference£¿
茶素茶，喝茶要分素幔
You northerners only have tea
@然，北方人喝茶
with melon seeds or peanuts
最多是吃吃瓜子 、 花生
We here are serious about having tea with food
我P州人最v究的是喝茶
Here's the best teahouse
@Y有壹家最有名的
The Merry Teahouse over there
就是前面的壹@
Merry Teahouse
壹@？
Go straight ahead,then turn right and there's an arch
朝前走，右D，有壹A拱T
That's the Merry Teahouse
那壹家就是壹@
Thank you
xx啊
Where are you going£¿ Come with me now
到哪汗砘欤靠旄我走
Sir,please go upstairs
客官，巧献
Old gentleman,this is hot water
老太，@是_水
It's bad to scald you,it's also bad to scald me
C了不好，C了我也不好
It's bad if someone is scalded
C了哪都不好
You're not the emperor, stop dashing around
以是皇帝，M_直撞
Lao San
老三
Waiter
夥
Ignore him
不要理他
Looks like he's a newcomer
好像第壹次P州
Bring me tea,bring me tea
_茶啊，_茶
Want to have tea£¿
喝茶啊？
I'm here for the tea
我砗炔
You haven't been here before,have you£¿
很好，@Y]有磉^吧？
This is the first time
第壹回
That's why you don't know our custom here
y怪不缘梦P州的矩
What custom£¿
喝茶有什麽矩？
Have you brought the tea leaves£¿
茶~]有？茶~呢？
I come here for tea
我砗炔璋
I know you're coming for tea
我缘砗炔
But you haven't brought your own tea leaves
]有Р枞~就到@Y砗炔枘
I come here for tea
我是砗炔璧
We don't have tea leaves here
@Y]有茶~
No£¿ How can you have tea without tea leaves£¿
]有？]有茶~怎麽喝茶？
You have to buy your own tea leaves
自己去I包茶~
We only offer water but not tea leaves
@Y是u水不u茶
Then don't call it a teahouse, this is a waterhouse
那不要叫茶^，叫水^好了吧
This is our custom here
@是我@Y的矩
Where should I go to buy the tea leaves£¿
那我到哪喝ベI啊？
See,that shop opposite the street
就有茶~u，看
Tea leaves are packed into small packages
@壹包壹包都包好的
Old gentleman,this is the best Longjin tea
@是最好的井，X，老太
Old gentleman£¿
老太？
Waiter
夥
Coming¡­
砹恕
Yes,old gentleman
老太
Is this for one pot or two pots
分壹次泡是苫兀
For one pot
壹次泡
Old gentleman,is this your first time in Yangzhou£¿
老太，^壹回到我P州？
Do you think I'm old£¿
X得我好老幔
Calling me ¡°old gentleman¡± all the time
左壹老太，右壹老太
Sir,there's a saying which goes £º
客官，俗Z有句
Boats all become small when they come to Guazhou
人到P州老，船到瓜州小
Because the harbour of Guazhou is very big
P子江瓜州的口子大
All boats seem small in comparison
S多大的船都@了小
We Yangzhou folk are very polite
我P州人v客
We call those in their thirties ¡°old gentleman¡±
三 、 四十q就叫老太
This is because you are polite
叫老太是客
If you're going further south
然了，要再往南走
People in Guangzhou are even more polite
到了V州就更客饬
They call everyone lao £¨old£©
什麽都是佬
Tall ones are gaolao
高的叫高佬
Fat ones are feilao
胖子叫肥佬
Bald ones are guangtaolao
]有^l的叫光^佬
Those with beard are husulao
有胡子的叫胡佬
Crazy ones are dianlao
子叫癫佬
ldiots are shalao
笨蛋叫傻佬
Weaklings are Kuilao
五谄叫佬
Strong ones are daizilao
三^六臂叫大只佬
Drunkards are zuijiulao
酒鬼叫醉酒佬
Womanizers are hanshilao
色鬼叫y窭
Thieves are zeilao
小偷叫\佬
Policemen are chailao
差的叫差佬
Older brother is dalao
哥哥叫大佬
Younger brother is xilao
弟弟叫佬
The ignorant is menglao
不明不白的叫懵佬
Gossipy like me is yashualao
我多嘴多舌的叫牙擦佬
Singles are gualao
]有老婆的叫寡佬
I have a wife¡­
我有老婆的…
She calls me shuailao all the time
她整天R我是衰佬
Why does she call you shuailao£¿
什麽R是衰佬？
Because I'm a kuilao
因我是佬嘛
What kind of lao is this fellow£¿
@小孩叫什麽佬？
He's not a lao,he's the older brother of lao
他比佬要老，是佬的哥哥
He's xilaoge
叫路哥
How about in Yangzhou dialect£¿
那P州呢？叫小老孩了？
We call him xiaolaodi
不叫小老孩，叫小老弟
Xiaolaodi
小老弟
Come here¡­
怼
What is this for£¿
@质谗幔
For having tea
喝茶啊
What are the chopsticks for£¿
要筷子质谗幔
People here are serious in tea drinking
我明白了，y怪P州吃茶考究
So you eat the tea leaves as well£¿
B茶~壹道吃啊？
No¡­this is for the meat jelly
不…@是吃肴肉的
Meat jelly£¿
肴肉？
Right¡­meat jelly is famous in Yangzhou
Α肴肉是我P州最有名的
Try some¡­
怼
At least have one piece
吃壹K算壹K
Is it okay to have meat with tea£¿
喝茶吃肉，不怕拉肚子
It's okay. Don't worry,old gentleman
不…老太放心
Meat is not the only food we have here
不止@肉，|西多得很
We have ribs,chicken and crab dumplings too
排骨u蒸蟹皇包佑
You can also have wine here
喜g喝酒的硭苫ǖ
If you don't drink wine you can have tea
不喝酒以茶代酒
No wonder they call this tea with food
怪不得f吃茶
A while back didn't you say you have crab dumplings£¿
才f的是蟹皇包？
Yes,dumplings with soup
Γ包
So you put dumplings in the soup£¿
包子煮在Y啊？
No¡­it's soup within the dumplings
不…是包子Y面有
You can't have this in the north
@是北方]有的
The emperor's cooks might be able to
不要看乾隆皇上的RN房
Prepare a grand imperial banquet
能蜃龅贸Mh全席
They can't make dumplings with soup inside
他就不能叫包子Y面有
Even the emperor would have never tasted this
蟹皇包，皇上都]吃^
Don't you believe this£¿
相不相信啊？
I believe
信
People said the emperor has been in Yangzhou
f皇上就到P州了
He should try this delicacy
Γ叫他__洋
Right¡­I want to try this delicacy too
好，我也__洋
Bring me some crab dumplings
替我硪蓟\蟹皇包
Okay
好
Old gentleman,your crab dumplings
老太，的蟹皇包
Would you like to add one or two extra ingredients£¿
要加壹的是加二的？
What does that mean£¿
加壹怎麽f？加二又怎麽v呢？
You can add more pork
加壹的多加ci肉
And more crab meat,just cost you a little bit more
加二的多加c蟹皇，不^多X
Okay,add whatever you like, just make them tasty
好，只要好吃，加三加四替我加
Money is not a problem
X]P系
Sure
就是啊
One order of crab dumplings, add 3 extra ingredients
蟹皇包壹\，要加三的啊
One order of crab dumplings,add 3 extras
蟹皇包壹\，加三
Please go upstairs
巧献
This meat jelly is good
@肴肉不e
Very tasty
瓜瓜叫
Here's your dumplings
包砹
Bastard,waiter
王八蛋，夥
Coming¡­
砹恕
Old gentleman,can I help£¿
老太，什麽事？
Bastard,there's so much soup inside
王八蛋，怎麽@麽多啊？
How can crab dumplings be without soup inside£¿
蟹皇包怎麽]有
And why didn't you warn me about that hot soup£¿
@麽C也不f壹
It doesn't look hot from the outside
看起硪键c不
That's why they're good dumplings
好就好在@
You don't know there's hot soup inside
看它不C，壹吃就C了
People often remark that the imperial banquet
所以有人v乾隆皇上吃Mh全席
Has all sorts of delicacies
三百六十樱吃壹，看二，眼^三
Except the crab dumplings of Yangzhou
就是]有^我P州的蟹皇包
Bastard
王八蛋
Waiter
夥啊
Coming
砹
Old gentleman,what else would you like£¿
老太，要吃c什麽？
No wonder there are many scholars from the south
怪不得江南出才子
Even a vegetable hawker can read
Bu菜的都念
He must be poor and can't afford to study
壹定是家境寒，]有X念
He has to work and to study
又要念又要做事
So now he's reading because the business is slow
所以忙Y偷e，半工半x
Poor fellow
可z啊
Poor£¿
可z？
Old gentleman,poor people are annoying
老太，可z之人必有可恨之
You tell people what you're selling
u什麽就咬喝什麽
You do what you have to do
做什麽就像什麽
But people like him
像他@拥娜
Just sit there reading but not selling his veggies
放著菜不u，念
Who knows what he's reading£¿
缘盟念什麽？
Must be some sort of erotic writings
不是金瓶梅就是肉蒲F
Or just rubbish
不然就是四季相思 、 打牙牌，念？
He's reading the Chunqiu, he can be a scholar
念到春秋，有翰林院的Y格了
Waiter
夥啊
Coming¡­
砹恕
How may I help£¿
什麽事啊？
Go and get that young man here
把那u菜的o我叫上
There's something I wish to ask him
我要PP他
What do you want to ask him£¿
P他？想他什麽？
I've heard that the emperor is coming to the south
f皇上@次下江南
in search of those well-learned scholars
是特Lt才的
My relative is a court official
我有H戚在朝Y做官
He comes to the south with the emperor
@壹次S{南
If that young guy is really a scholar
如果他有真材W的
I'll take him to my relative
我替他引引
He might be offered a job in the government
o他壹官半的
It's better than being in the street
也免得他流落街^
Old gentleman,just mind your own business
老太，多壹事不如少壹事
I know this young guy
@小夥子我J得他
His name is Zhou Reqing
他姓周，叫周日清
His uncle is Zhou Jianfeng
他有壹叔叔叫周Ψ
Zhou Jianfeng£¿
周Ψ澹
The one who used to work in the lmperial Academy£¿
是不是以前在翰林院的周Ψ澹
Yes,he used to work there
Γ以前是翰林院的
Now he's retired and returned to his hometown
F在告老l，在家YB病
Zhou is a just and virtuous official
@周Ψ官清正 、 品高和寡
So he didn't make much money
如今落得尚淝屣L 、 家如洗
He has some paintings that could be worth something
有些字值X
But he insists not to sell them
可是他甯死不u
His nephew is now supporting him
全靠他@侄褐苋涨遒u菜度日
But Reqing is not working hard enough
不缘眠@周日清又吊豪僧
He doesn't care about his business
不好好的做生意
And keeps studying all day
挑起子在念
Always talking about books
子曰，，之乎者也
If he doesn't study,he practices martial arts
放下子，刀棍棒拳打_踢
Thinking he's both a literary and martial arts master
自以是文武p全
He has such pride and ambition
于是也就目空四海好高骛h
If you give him the job of a military general
介B兵R大元o他
He might think this is too trivial for him
他嫌官小呢
He has high aspirations but he's unfortunate
心比天高，命比薄
He can't earn his capital back
不要v指望他X
Let alone making a profit
他每天B本X都u不回
He also owes huge debts
外面欠了壹屁股
Trouble will find its way to him
早晚是麻
I think you should forget about this guy
照我看，@N人是少理吧
Military general
兵R大元
Veggie military general
兵R大青菜
Carrot military general
兵R大}N
See,I told ya trouble will find him
看啊，我v他有麻
Now here comes the trouble
麻┚砹
Officers
晌唬晌卉
You should pay up now,shouldn't you£¿
@X交了吧？
I don't have the money
我]有啊
No money£¿ And you're studying here, bastard
]有？他的，]有在念
Why don't you do your business now£¿
不快做生意
Yes¡­
是…
I am going to do business now
我@就去做生意
What£¿ You're not convinced
什麽？不服猓
This is too much
太不像
This is the fifth day,5 dollars a day
第五天了，B今天，五X壹天
The total adds up to 25 dollars
五五二十五，壹共是二十五X
It'll be 30 tomorrow
明天就是三十了
So how about paying up¡­
今天@二十五X
the 25 dollars today£¿
到底o不o？
Do you hear me£¿
]有？
Please,I really have no money
兔Γ我在]有
What do you mean by no money£¿
不行，什麽叫]有？
We wouldn't have a cent if everyone was like you
全像@樱我X怎麽收？
I know you're poor so I let you delay for a few days
我是看可z，叫耽R商
But now you're delaying day after day
倒壹天壹天的拖下去
Every day you say ¡°tomorrow¡±
今天推明天，明天推後天
What kind of tricks you're playing
_什麽玩笑？
I'm not playing tricks
我在]有
See,I can't even sell vegetables
看我的菜都u不出去
Can't sell£¿
u不出去？
Then why don't you just go and sell them now£¿
u不出去不快cu
Study£¿ If people like you can study
念？就{@副德性念得出
Then everyone can be an official
朝廷Y的官都站不下了
If you can study,you can be the emperor
要念得出恚皇上都做了
Now give me the money
快c把X交出
Sorry¡­my uncle is sick
Σ黄稹因我叔叔有病
I need the money to buy medicine for him
每天uX都o他I了
If he could get well again¡­
要是能虬堰@病治好…
No
不行
If you don't pay,you can't leave
今天不oX，就^不了@T
Officers,please be kind¡­
晌蛔鲎龊檬拢…
What£¿ Let me tell you
？什麽？我告V
It's no use to delay
壹毛不拔也不是k法
Tomorrow is the 6th day, day after tomorrow is 7th
明天六天，後天就七天
Your debt rolls bigger and bigger, like a snowball
雪球是越L越大
If you pay a little today and a little tomorrow
今天付壹c，明天付壹c
Then you'll clear up your debt
慢慢不就付完了幔
Well,we want to be kind to you
老是@樱我不是不做好事
But our situation is difficult too
@NX我是深^不好
Our supervisors think we've spent the money
上^以我用了
In fact we haven't got any
在我]收著
If everyone delays like you
全像@
Then we'll be finished
我不就更玩和炅
You have to understand that
要知道
We can't spend event a cent of this money
@NX我用不到壹分壹毫
This is imperial taxes
@X是皇命X
All the money has to go to Beijing
收R了都要拿到京Y去
And be given to Emperor Chien Lung to spend
交o乾隆皇上用的
What money£¿ For me to spend£¿
什麽X？交o我的？
I never use this money
@X我]有用到
It's so strange
奇怪
Waiter
夥啊
Old gentleman,what's the matter£¿
老太，什麽事？
What kind of money they're collecting downstairs£¿
@窍乱的是什麽X？
This£¿ Downstairs£¿
窍拢@啊？
What money£¿
什麽X啊？
What money£¿ You tell me
什麽X？fo我
I'll tell you
我vo
Come here
戆
You can tell me just right here
要f就在@赫f
Why are you being so stealthy£¿
鬼鬼崇崇的质谗幔
ldiot,just come with me
蠢材，我叫跟我砺
I want you to tell me right here
我要在@赫f
You idiot,come here
@胡T蛋，
Come¡­
怼
Come here
戆
This money¡­
@X…
Sit down¡­
坐…
Tell me,what's this money for£¿
f，@到底是什麽X？
Old gentleman,this money
@X啊，老太
I'm okay if I didn't talk about it
我不v我不
When I start talking about it I'm getting angry
他的，我壹v，我饩砹
What's this money for£¿ Tell me
@是什麽X？f
You can't blame other people
@X不怪旁人
But that Emperor Chien Lung, son-of-a-bitch
就怪@婊子B的乾隆皇帝
He gives us citizens a hard time
他把我老百姓害苦了
I wonder how such an emperor
@皇帝硭榔
will die in the future
不缘迷貅死法
Don't curse people
不要_口就R人嘛
Why are you cursing people£¿
R人质谗幔
Honestly
我不mv
Well,this is me
我@脾饩褪沁@幼
I only curse those who deserve to be cursed
我要R的壹定要R
Honestly,even if Emperor Chien Lung was here
老v，就是乾隆皇帝在我@
I won't shut up. I won't be polite to him
我也是要R，我是不uさ
That son of a bitch
@王八蛋的|西
Tell me,what's that money for£¿
v吧，@到底是什麽X？
This money¡­
@X呐
Actually we didn't have to pay this money before
@X以前是]有的
Last spring,when Emperor Chien Lung
去年春天，@乾隆皇帝在mY^
was having fun in his imperial palace
左碛冶В前摸後摸
He passed an order
于是他就下了壹道旨意
Shit,this emperor really spends a lot of money
他的，@皇帝啊_N可大了
On what would be spend so much on£¿
他有什麽_N呢？
Shit,he has dozens of imperial concubines
他的，三m六院七十二嫔妃
They have shark's fin and other delicacies every day
~翅 、 燕C 、 海 、 鹿茸
There's not enough money in the national treasure
煅Y的X不蛴昧
And he knows that Yangzhou is a wealthy place
他就想到P州是~米之l好地方
So he sends over a minister
他就派了壹大臣姓~的
Ye Hongjun
叫~洪x
To come here and set up a tax office
到@Yk了壹捐局
Tax office£¿
捐局？
Everyone doing business has to pay tax
做生意Iu都要付捐
Shop proprietors have to pay 100 dollars
譬方_店的要壹百X
Or maybe 50 dollars
五十X都不壹定
Those small businesses and hawkers
[小^的，做小Iu的
They might have to pay 10 to 20 dollars
二十的，十的
Even the smallest business has to pay tax
拿@子的都要X啊
He has to pay at least 5 dollars
他挑子的，五X
If you didn't have 5 dollars you couldn't do business
]有五X就不能到街上磙D
When the money is collected
他@X弄到手
Every cent is sent to Beijing for Chien Lung's pleasure
yy送到京城o他去用
Old gentleman,not only Yangzhou
老太，非但是P州
It'd be okay even if it's just Yangzhou
P州也就T了
Even areas around Yangzhou have to pay tax
他是准
You see,this is a huge amount of income
想想看他@Mた删筒坏昧
The taxing period was for a year
本硎且寄
From last spring to this spring
去年春天到今年壹年
Now Dragon Boat Festival is approaching
F在端快到了
And he's still getting good money
是啊，他壹想，不e，生意不e
So the period is extended for another year
要加多壹年
Then the people will have more difficult times
哎呀，老百姓的日子可就苦了
Old gentleman,do you still think I'm wrong£¿
老太，想我R得e不e啊？
Son of a bitch,bastard
他的，婊子B的，O子
Damn it,bastard
他的，@王八蛋的|西
If I had used this money
@X我要是用^
I really deserve to be cursed
人家RR也是的
But I'd never use a cent
可是我]有用^啊
You£¿ It's good if he gave you some
用？他不要o就算好了
Officer,please give me a few more days
，限商彀
How much should he pay£¿ I'll pay for him first
他交多少X，我先|出
You'll pay for him£¿ You have a big family
|？有八百多口子
How can you pay for him£¿
|得起幔
It's none of your business,get lost
狗拿耗子，多管e事，L_
Son of a bitch
他的
Give me the money
他的，oX
I don't have any
]有
No£¿
]有？
Even if you beat me to death
打死我也]有
You really want to die£¿
他的，找死了？
I have no money
]有
You sure have a lot of nerve !
好小子
Good
好
Good¡­very good
好啊…好…
Want to fight back£¿
想造反啊？
What are you doing£¿
质谗幔
Good
好
Very good
好啊
Left strike,right strike
左勾拳，右勾拳
Don't look like a fool
e愣著啊
Good,good strike
好，打得好
Son of a bitch
他的
Watch your back
心後面
Be careful
心
Five Phoenix Facing the Sun
五P朝
Monkey stealing the Peach
O猴偷桃
Good
好啊
A turtle rolling over the door
觚翻T啊
Shit,I'll kill you
他的，我宰了
At your back
後面
Good¡­beat him¡­good¡­
好…打…好…
Tell me,what do you want to eat
二位，要吃什麽|西，f嘛
I am going to bring you food
我拿o的
Son of a bitch
他的
Go¡­get lost¡­
走…L_…
Who's yelling£¿ Who's there£¿
l叫好？什麽人叫好？
Come over,come over now
出恚快出
Who's yelling£¿
l叫好？
Crab dumplings with 3 extras
小\包，加三啊
Don't you know there's a dish in the imperial banquet£¿
圆缘Mh全席有壹道菜
What dish£¿
什麽菜？
Make a hole in the center of the table
在桌中央挖洞，把^伸出
A head pokes out,strike it with a hammer
用小FN就@麽壹敲
Use a spoon to have some fresh brain
拿匙吃rX
Human brain£¿
人X？
No¡­monkey brain
不…猴X
Take that table away
把桌子o我拿掉
Take it away now
快o我拿下
Chief,I would take it away if I could
，能拿掉不早o拿掉了
But it's stuck on you
它就是拿不掉啊
It does have a hole at the center
@中g正好有窟窿
Bring it back and have a hot pot then
拿回去吃火吧
Bullshit
的，找死啊
This is bullshit,son of a bitch
@才叫找死，他的O子
It's you£¿
是啊？
It's me
是我
Well done
值煤
Come on
上
Kid,if you did have guts,don't go
好小子，有Ne走
Come here,I'm waiting
砗昧耍我等著
I dare pull the emperor down even if I have to die
拼了壹身，皇上拉下R
Bastard
王八蛋
Old gentleman,it isn't the bastard
老太，不是王八蛋
It's getting lost
直是L蛋
Kid,let's have tea
小老弟，我喝茶去
Go and have some tea
喝茶去
I¡­
我…
Old gentleman,I can't have tea with you
老太，我怎麽能跟壹K去喝茶
It doesn't matter. Come¡­
@有什麽P系，怼
Old gentleman,I don't want to¡­
老太，我不去…
Forget it,come and have tea with me
ef@麽多，跟我喝茶去
It's closed
都上了板了
Old gentleman
老太
Thank you for helping us
xx您路不平，拔刀相助
But this is big trouble you've made
我看@J得不小
It's because of me,it has nothing to do with you
事情因我而起，c人o尤
I'll take all the responsibility
壹切由我沓
Please leave now or you'll be in trouble
您老s快x_此地，免得受窟B
What£¿
什麽？
I'm a colleague of your uncle in the lmperial Academy
我跟叔叔周Ψ逶诤擦衷和事
Don't worry,whatever happened
放心，天塌下
I'll take care of it
有我
No,old gentleman,I'll be responsible for this
不，老太，壹人做事壹人
I dare pull the emperor down even if I have to die
拼了壹身，皇帝拉下R
Old gentleman,my uncle is sick now
老太，我叔叔他在病中
If something happened to me
我要有三L啥
Please help me to take care of him
望您老念在^去同事的份上
Because you're his ex-colleague
能蛘疹照他
I'll pay back your generosity
硎雷雠Ｗ鲴R
in the hereafter
也蟠鹉的大恩大德
Get up¡­
起怼
Let's get inside and have some tea
蹦了半天，咱到Y面喝杯茶去
And get some rest too
歇口
Open up¡­
_T…
Old gentleman,you both have to leave now
老太，不跑
I can't be responsible
自己J的
For the trouble you've made
要我陪去死啊
Don't worry,we just want some tea
不要怕，我要喝口茶，
Tea£¿ We have family events today
喝茶？今天我家有要事
And we're closed
不做生意
Don't worry
不要怕
I'll take care of everything
壹切啊有我
You£¿
有啊？
Are you serious£¿
有就]有我了
Well,I haven't paid my bill
那我的み]算啊
The boss said it's on him
我老板f他客了
How about those broken things£¿
@打的|西呢？
They can't be just broken like that
不能白打啊
I'll pay for them too. Tell me how much
算壹算多少X，我碣r
The boss said
r啊？老板回家之前交代^的
You don't have to pay for those things
不用r了
We're just having bad luck
算我自己倒q
To be born in such a bad time
l叫我生在@年^啊
With such a bastard emperor
碰@王八蛋的皇上啊
Son of a bitch
婊子B的O子
Why¡­are you cursing again£¿
…怎麽又R人呐？
Dear old gentleman,let me tell you
我的老太，我告V
If you're lucky you would have a good emperor
要是命好呢，s上真天子
The country would be peaceful and prosperous
那就泰民安 、 L{雨
But now we have this shitty Emperor Chien Lung
他的我遇到@乾隆皇帝
This Chien Lung
@乾隆
Chien Lung means ¡°too much dryness¡±
乾隆就是乾隆
All the water is drunk by him alone
水都被他壹人喝
And we're all finished
老百姓不完蛋嘛
Chien Lung is really awful
乾隆可不得了
When he comes over
他要壹
Don't even think of having water
想喝茶
Let alone having tea,old gentleman
B_水都]得喝了，老太
Please bring us two stools
拿凳子我坐坐嘛
Stools£¿
凳子？
What you should have is the prison
有得坐的，O牢Y的老虎凳
Even if you don't want to be there
想不坐也不成，老太
Bastard
王八蛋
Old gentleman,please sit here
老太，您@鹤
Okay¡­
好…
Why are you sitting here£¿
怎麽坐在@海
Would you please sit somewhere else£¿
到e去坐好不好？
People have to go through this door
我@T口要走路的
Okay
好
Old gentleman,this is a doorway
老太，@是路口
We have to use this doorway, please go away
我要走路的，好狗不趼
It's just minor trouble
@麽c小事
See¡­you're so frightened
看…就成@幼
Minor trouble£¿ It's not minor, dear old gentleman
小事啊？不小了，我的老太
You see,this big building
看，我@麽大的
is almost torn down by you
差壹c就o拆光了
Listen
我v
You've interfered officers' duty
阻差k公，罪加壹等
And you've beaten them,this is against the law
打差人，就是藐法律
And you've disturbed public order
看，@就是_y治安
Now you're sitting here and this is loitering
F在坐在@海就是oI[
If you don't have to be executed for these crimes
六l大罪，不打壹死罪
At least you have to stay in jail for life
也要判o期
Please,old gentleman
兔Π。老太
If you don't want to leave
叫走，不走
At least you keep the way clear,okay£¿
壹路可以的吧
Okay,I don't want to bring trouble to you
好啊，免得B累
So I'll sit in the middle of the road
我坐在路中g
This should be okay,bastard
壹家壹半可以吧，王八蛋
You're obstructing traffic, it's an offense too
@幼幼锛右嫉龋阻街
It's them
就是他
Is that him£¿
是他幔
Yes
是
It's me
是我
It's you£¿
是？
None of your business,ignore him
不P的事？不要他
I'll be responsible for everything
壹切我沓
How dare you
好大的子
Who make the first move£¿
他l先邮值模
Both of them
他都有邮
It's him,he made the first move
是他，他先拥氖
Want to disobey government officials, right£¿
想造反是不是？
And dare to beat up police officers
竟敢打公差
State your names and where you're from
笊的姓名籍
I'm Gao Tianci
我姓高，叫高天n
From Beijing
是北京天府人士
Are you Ye Hongjun of the tax office£¿
是捐局的~洪x幔
You're impolite to call my name and title like that
本官的官I是S便叫的幔
You do have some nerve,Ye Hongjun
~洪x，好大的
You're lying about the Emperor's order
假髀}旨，私O捐局
And collect taxes for your private use
征收苛捐s
This is very serious,don't you know£¿
知道何罪幔
Master¡­
大人…
Master
大人
Who is this guy£¿
@人是l？
I don't know who he is
我也不知道他是l？
What's his background£¿ What's he doing here£¿
他是什麽眩康降资质谗岬模
He has Beijing accent,his name is Gao Tianci
北京口音，姓高，名叫高天n
Gao Tianci£¿
高天n？
There's an implication in his speech
他的Y^有骨^
He must be sent by Beijing
恐怕是京Y派淼
He's from Beijing£¿
京Y派淼模
Looks like he's the Emperor
看幼酉袷腔噬
The Emperor£¿ You've met him,don't you£¿
皇上？不是接^{幔
Yes
是啊
Take a closer look
看清楚壹c
I'll take a good look
我去看清楚
Isn't he the Emperor£¿
是不是皇上？
I'm not sure
看不太清楚
He's just right here and you're not sure£¿
@麽近不清楚？
It's too close
就是太近了嘛
When I met the Emperor,he was miles away
我接{的r候，x皇上有八丈h啊
Then stay further
那站hc嚎
Isn't he the Emperor£¿
是不是皇上？
If he's not the Emperor,who could he be£¿
不是皇上，是l啊？
Your Majesty
皇上
Rong An is late,please forgive me
臣鄂容安接{磉t，罪f死
Long live Your Majesty
fqfqffq
Your Majesty
皇上
Now I am a ¡°shuai lao¡±
@壹下我成了衰佬了
I'm a ¡°shuai lao¡±
我成了衰佬了
Arise¡­
起怼
Old gentleman¡­no¡­Your Majesty
老太…不…皇上
Don't be afraid
不要怕
I come here to look for virtuous people
我@次南巡的本意就是Lt
And to understand the lives of my people
c深入民g了解老百姓之苦
And I want my people to know more about me
也叫老百姓多知道朝廷Y的事情
You didn't know who I am,so I'm not mad at you
天高皇帝h，不知者不怪罪
Zhou Riqing
周日清
Yes
在
You just said even if you have to die
才f拼了壹身
What's next£¿
下句是什麽啊？
I'll pull the horse for the Emperor
拼了壹身，也要替皇上拉著R
Good
好
The 11th month of the 1 6th year of Chien Lung's reign
乾隆十六年的十壹月二十五日
¡­was the Queen Mother's 60th birthday celebration
是皇太後的六十大
At her birthday banquet all the common people
在c民同返垩缟
were as drunk as if they were some lords
@些善良的老百姓都喝得醉如泥
Chien Lung was 41 at that time
r的乾隆是四十壹q
It was 1752A.D.
就是公元壹七五二年